"Some mines have very good conditions
有些矿井环境条件很好
and some are very bad," says Wu Xiang, the crew chief.
工头吴翔说 有些矿井环境却很糟糕
"Once you get used to this, it's not a big problem."
一旦你习惯了就不是什么大问题
What about the coal dust?
那煤尘呢
"The dust is harmful to our health,
煤尘对我们的健康有害
but l don't think it's a big deal," he says.
但我想没什么大不了 他说
"Once we start using the mask and other protection measures,
只要我们使用面具和采取其他保护措施
we should be fine."
我们应该会没事
This year, with China facing growing coal shortages,
今年由于中国面临持续增长的煤炭短缺
they also worked through the Lunar New Year's holiday.
中国农历新年的假期期间他们依然在工作
The miners are celebrated in plastic icons and photographs.
矿工们用塑料图标和照片庆祝
Coal, after all, has made Datong a relatively affluent
煤炭毕竟使大同成为这片
in an area of great poverty.
贫困地区中一个相对富裕的地方
Normally, the mine shuts down during this 10-day holiday,
一般来说 春节期间煤矿会关闭十天
but many parts of China have been hit this year
但今年中国很多地方
with a record-breaking cold wave.
遇到前所未有的煤炭寒潮
You'll note that most of the dancers
你注意到大部分的舞者
are women partnering up with one another.
是女性们结伴在跳舞
The men are down in the mine, working overtime.
男人们却在矿井里加班加点地工作
"We are responding to the country's needs," he says.
他说 我们这是在响应国家的需求
"ln some places, they have to ration."
一些地方不得不限量供应
How much extra did they pay you
在春节期间工作
for working the Lunar New Year?
他们多付给你多少钱
"Three times our salary," he says.
三倍的工资 他说
Is your wife happy about that,
你妻子对此感到开心吗
or would she rather have had you off for the holiday?
还是她宁愿你回家过年
"When she sees the money," he says,
她看到钱时 他说
"she'll be very happy."
她会开心的
ln this mine,there are no picks and shovels.
在这个矿井里没有镐和铲
lt's all highly mechanized.
全部高度机械化